chapter 8 is called active inference and
continuous time begins with that
Timeless quote everything flows nothing
stands still
what would you say about chapter eight
all right so this chapter probably is my
most favorite chapter in the book uh
because of my own personal interests and
uh I don't know the process materialism
and so on but uh yeah so chapter seven
um
it acts as a really good starting point
for anyone who wants to
develop the discrete time situations and
to model the screen time situations uh
inactive within active inference
framework but in chapter 8 we kind of
get into get to
a Model A bit more interesting or let's
say more involving situations uh and
they're not necessarily uh
kind of toy examples we saw at least at
the beginning of chapter seven uh so uh
obviously as the title suggests this
chapter deals with the continuous time
situation so uh in the in that case
we'll need to
and maybe at this point
um refresh our memory about what
continuous time situation involves by
reading the relevant Parts reading
reading relevant parts of chapter four
so
uh yeah in chapter four we saw that the
generative model for continuous time
situation uh derives derives from uh the
uh stochastic calculus in terms of
putting the whole process
into two elements uh two stochastic two
elements of stochastic equations one of
which is the actual State the condition
of actual States or the behavior of the
actual States and the other one is the
randomness that we need to account for
in each real-time continuous time
situations so that's what we get here in
equation eight a eight point one and
then building up from that equation uh
we
um it generalizes that equation to
involve uh I mean
the fun the functionals of G and F
instead of just the
[Music]
um
the single valued functions of G and F
so uh then we get to
put that into uh the situation that can
be used for describing the behavior
dynamical systems which is a very
well-known uh situation to use these
kinds of stochastic equations and it's
widely studied how those those kinds of
Dynamics can be characterized especially
in recent Bayesian mechanics paper by
Dalton sectivitavel and others so
and then it gets to some more specific
examples such as a lockable terror
Dynamics and synchronicity and so on in
order to show how these kinds of
Dynamics can be
elaborated upon and can be generalized
to
and and enables them to characterize a
more complex situations so
uh
yeah that's a really short and brief
overview of the whole uh chapter maybe
uh we can talk about a bit more details
as we go through
right well said well I'm sure for
another day the philosophical
implications of eight seven and eight
and high road and low road all these
other parts of the textbook great topics
um I I agree I would see chapter 8 as
demonstrating continuity
with some classical
continuous time modeling motifs from a
few different areas of dynamical Systems
Science which is applied in like many
many many fields but these are some
classical examples so figure 8.1 goes a
little bit more into depth or at least
into more formalism detail about exactly
what we saw in chapter five with the
spinal reflex arc with the
proprioceptive data coming in and then a
differential being calculated with the
set point which reflects a descending
prediction from a decision-making layer
and that can be viewed as this kind of
mechanics that plays out in a phase
space in continuous time like a spring
moving around with with someone making a
certain path with an attractor and a
spring being dragged around something in
that area
box 8.1 goes into a very fascinating
topic do you want to describe it
uh well uh it's uh maybe one of the most
um thought-provoking uh section pages of
the whole book and if I remember
correctly uh in all of the cohorts this
particular box
I mean gives always gives rise to lots
of questions uh because of some of the
interesting and uh at least initially
counter-intuitive
claims here but I don't want to spoil it
so
um
but as a kind of spoiler alert it kind
of
gets to
a really interesting but uh alas very
brief discussion about the comparing
these terms Precision attention and
sensory the attenuation and the relation
and similarities and difference between
these two these three terms and how each
understanding each of them is essential
to understanding uh the other ones but
as I said it's a really interesting
topic which gives rise to lots of
discussions
and I believe it's one of those
topics that that's worth looking a bit
more uh looking into in some other
literature as well
great well set what a cliffhanger
next they go to a classic Model family
called lockabletera
these Dynamics inherit from
characterizations of Predator prey
Dynamics in ecology
so it's kind of a classical ecology
model shown in figure 8.2 on the top
it's actually the ecosystem model plants
herbivores and carnivores which follow
different kinds of oscillatory Trends in
continuous time
and so that also has enabled it to be
applied for other so-called winnerless
competitions and that relates to topics
like neural Darwinism and also
neurodynamics where things have kind of
oscillatory relationships with each
other which are being modeled as a
continuous time underlying process
with a lot of measurement noise and
discretization through space and time
those are the kinds of algorithms that
SPM explores more and there's lack of
Volterra and a lot of other dynamical
systems theory in SPM
so active inference kind of adds action
and more to what was laid out from a
pure dynamical systems theory in SPM
here it really is just showing the
ecology example and how you can project
if you have three different species you
can think about that motion in a cube or
tetrahedron and then you could project
onto kind of like uh looking at a lower
dimensional manifold relating just two
of the three species and that advances
this kind of oscillatory but also moving
Behavior
that gets connected in figure 8.3 to
neurobiology what would you say about
this
uh okay so here in figure 8.3 uh we see
some applications of
um a lock of Altera Dynamics uh so uh
the left column uh here uh represents
um what happens in I mean in eye
blinking eye blink conditioning so uh of
course here we need to account for uh I
mean the expected States
of uh of the of the sequel of the
sequences of events that happens in in
the eye blinking so uh the upper
upper left figure shows the expectations
uh in terms of time and then
uh the parallel right hand side equation
sorry right hand side figures uh shows
the uh
the lock of Altera system that that is
applied
um in the handwriting situation so as we
can see although uh the uh I mean
mathematical technology is the same or
at least the modeling technology is the
same
the outcome of each situation uh varies
drastically in
two distinct
um
the two distinct neurobiological
Behavior not neurobiological but
biological Behavior Uh so yeah we can
see how the same modeling framework can
give rise to
different uh outcomes uh based on what
parameters is needs to be optimized what
parameters are selected for the modeling
and so on so I believe it's a quite
uh interesting example to compare
handwriting and the blinking together
and how those can be compared to each
other using the last laughable Terror
Dynamics
great thank you
box 8.2 gives a variance on the learning
here presented with the formalism for
continuous models kind of a technical
aside
section 8.4 is about generalized
synchrony so figure 8.4 is going to
visualize one of the classic dynamical
systems which is the Lorenz attractor so
what would you say about this
figure okay so this section is uh truly
interesting because uh
when one thinks of active inference
probably the first situations that comes
to mind is uh the situations in which we
have a quite well-defined uh probability
distributions for different parameters
but as we can see here in
section 8.4 actually some of the
formalism of active inference can be
successfully used to characterize even
chaotic systems and protect and in
particular the way in which two chaotic
systems can be synchronized with each
other so this is a classic example of a
chaotic Lorenz system uh and um it
derives from it draws upon uh from some
of a professor person's earlier work on
Birdsong synchrony
and as a side note any literature before
2016 is considered earlier history in
active inference literature because it
evolves uh quite rapidly so
uh yeah this kind of synchrony between
two chaotic systems uh can be
interpreted as providing evidence or
even
let's say a way to model a kind of
primitive theory of mind uh in in the
sense that how exactly can we
understand uh or can two two agents can
trace each other's trajectories uh
without
um any I mean engaging in any direct
exchange of observations between their
internal and external States so uh yeah
that's a really good example and I
believe one of the most interesting
examples of how active inference can
even account for these kinds of uh
Behavior so
and the rest of the section goes into
the details of how this kind of
synchrony between
um multi multi-scale uh Birds
multi-scale Lorenz systems can happen
um and how can we
formulate it mathematically in terms of
continuous time active inference
awesome and there's been more recent
work on Markov blankets and stochastic
chaos but the bird example is a classic
8.5 goes into hybrid discrete and
continuous models so this could be kind
of like a in-between chapter of seven
and eight but now that we've been
introduced to the pure form of discrete
in the pure form of continuous models
here shown the dot composability extends
to so-called Hybrid models where here
the lower level visually is using the
continuous time formalism
and the higher level is describing the
little line added here the discrete time
formalism and this was the similar
structure described by the authors of
the paper octave inference does not
contradict folk psychology
where they describe this lower level as
motor active inference which was closely
allied with the spinal Arc reflex shown
above and then this higher level they
call decision active inference because
in that case it was referring to a
discrete decision
and so they used that kind of basic
motif of continuous activity or
continuous time modeling at the more
peripheral aspects of a cognitive entity
and like Ali said more discretization
[Music]
and hybridization as well at higher
levels of the cognitive modeling
and that type of an architecture here
instead of describing who wants the ice
cream cone I believe
here it's gonna be a mixed or hybrid
model that is going to call back the
isocade
system
where there's a fixed point
that is able to be moved as a set point
and then there's a continuous time
isocade that pursues the new fixed point
so that's analogous to a new set point
or fixed point being specified from the
top down muscle command about a new
location for a muscle followed by
movement towards it this is a muscular
activity that is realizing that but but
not in the elbow coming away from the
hot stove this is about the eye cicading
to an epistemic foraging location
specified by top down hierarchical
systems
8.3 describes little technical aside on
mixture of gaussian gaussian mixture
models kind of a
technical modeling note an 8.6 closes
it says it's a huge topic and much has
been left out and so they list in table
8.1 key advances in continuous time
models and those areas are
synthetic bird song
ocular motor delays
conditioned reflexes smooth Pursuit eye
movements psychosis illusions cicades
action observation attention Hybrid
models and self-organization
and that's chapter 8. what else would
you say and also what would you kind of
lead someone to in the philosophical
implications of eight because it sounds
kind of cool
uh okay so
uh well the case of continuous time
active inference uh
uh
I think it leads to
a really interesting questions uh both
in terms of uh philosophical questions
and also uh a more practical modeling
questions about uh what parameters needs
to be accounted for and so on uh and as
I said I believe it's a more more
interesting way of
um if not interesting but but at least
more involved way of doing active
inference modeling but uh one thing that
uh one of the philosophical questions
that um
have explored uh in our paper is how
the processes of I mean ontological
processes can
uh philosophically described using fpp
assertions in terms of their intraction
with the environment
[Applause]
in which they co-constitute themselves
and we don't necessarily
distinguish between uh between the
internal and the external state so one
obvious example of this is that
generalized synchrony example that we
saw in this chapter in which we don't
necessarily distinguish between which of
the birds act as
the agents and which one is the um
environment or the vice versa so these
kind of co-constitution of the
environment and the agent which gives
rise to the partitioning of State space
through a markup blanket is uh one of
the interesting uh
philosophical points that I think needs
to be elaborated
a bit more using and some of the recent
advances in philosophy such as the two
the tools that's been developed in new
materialism
school or some other philosophical
approach approaches but yeah these kinds
of uh what exactly gives size gives rise
to emergence what is the ontological
status of emergent properties and so on
are some of the
um
burning questions for many philosophers
today and I believe active inference in
particularly continuous time active
inference provides a clear
precise
mathematical formalism uh even if not to
answer these questions but at least to
explore it in a more rigorous and uh
practical way and also
practical and attractive attractable way
so this is the area that I believe uh
philosophy and science uh are
beautifully intertwined uh into a
coherent view of not only
the phenomenon of interest but even
about the whole world
wow
wow pretty cool yeah a lot to say about
that topic
after completing chapter seven and eight
you've seen the kind of two major
branches or two major motifs of just one
kind of modeling but these kind of
models have so many different forms that
that's why it's such a Hands-On process
to specify the generative model in
chapter six and fit it with data in
chapter nine those are all what's
required and that's kind of the last
mile of where these discussions about
General motifs gets you
but also playing with these pedagogical
models can be really helpful because it
will help you understand the basic
patterns and relationships and start to
see see different patterns in the
graphical models and know from there
what levels of technical processes can
be kind of coarse grained over